we are live welcome to our idea cafe I'm
gonna say first one because the first
one we have two other people show up for
it's really the second one and so
today's question is what is a common
critique you get about your project in a
and idea cafe everyone takes up to five
minutes to share we might want to keep
it a little close if you could go less
than five minutes that was perfectly
fine it's also okay to pass especially
for someone who let's say doesn't have a
project that wants to be part of the
open conversation at the end I'm always
happy to start or go last or go at any
point when there is another moment of
silence so who would like to start in
answering the question right and then
everyone else can just mute so yeah so a
quick overview my project it's reason
score it's a tool for helping people
come to agreement over contentious
issues the the part of the most common
counter I get when I am describing it is
that's impossible it's just hard to
believe that you can find a tool that
can help or that you know here's here's
a reason that yeah that you can't it
uses numbers in math and some
quantifications and they say you can't
quantify decision-making and that's true
to an extent but having the numbers kind
of helps so that's that's the most
common I think that's the most common
kind of complaint I get about it when
I'm trying to describe the initial do
the initial pitch oh yeah a lot of
people just don't like putting having a
computer give you numbers on a decision
they're having to make they seem to find
that repulsive and they can't explain to
me why yeah I'm working as people so
that's my answer
thanks Bentley who would like to go next
reduce razor handle and meet you or I
can go alright Brad I'll write a brief
overview of my project is a urban
agriculture venture in Columbus Ohio
where we live my wife and I the it's a
social enterprise so we're trying to
solve a social problem mainly food
deserts the part of town I live in is
becoming a through desert in the south
part in the east part are currently
through deserts meaning they don't have
access to fresh fruits and vegetables so
our gas stations are closing down and
then stores are popping up inside the
old gas stations selling just box goods
some people are losing their lack of
produce so we're trying to remedy that
the common critique that I get is it's a
little bit too utopian specifically you
know this is what the market wants if
like the market didn't support this type
of thing it wouldn't happen so there's a
reason for happening which I agree there
is a reason it's not a good one in my
opinion so we're trying to solve that
and trying to prove something critics
wrong saying this is a project people
like Bill Gates and other people should
attend to and I'd say a members
community that's caught up in that sort
of thing so that's a word trying to up
the salt Ford
guys like myself right
I'm a drill my project is wiki election
it is attempting to yes solve the
problem of misinformation so in a bit of
a hard one because part of the critique
is I think not one people have
explicitly said but it's definitely
implied where they just have a problem
understanding it where it's sort of two
conceptual right now and it's trying to
do a lot of different things I think one
of the actual critiques that I've gotten
is just how are you kind of going to
deal with trolls and people trying to
lie and people sort of trying to argue
their viewpoint on the platform haha how
would you counter that and a big part of
just having an emphasis on evidence and
kind of like what families talking about
trying to quantify that conversation
trying to sort of figure out how you can
actually put kind of a more quantitative
and qualitative approach to dissecting
it so if you can see where the evidence
actually lies who agrees with it that
kind of thing which as you can probably
tell there is a long answer and as part
of the challenge with explaining it
right that sounds like a you're done so
it's is okay all I need Susan okay so
the project that I've been working on
for the last year is called the two row
flow cultural Commons and basically it
is a emerging space for settlers and
first peoples to make sense out of our
treaty relationship or relationships and
there are a couple common narratives
that have been established so we're
working to try to have discussion around
those to start as anyone who knows can I
just get a raise of hands who who
considers himself to be a settler okay
yeah so typically one of the first
critiques could be as to the word
settler as opposed to first peoples
because there's also immigrants but
there is a historical
president or in a historic history
behind this relationship which the
deeper you go into it the more totally
solid it is in fact the entire so-called
Canada is based on treaties by this
something that we're not taught as
settlers and so the idea of actually
revisiting something that was even prior
to the founding of this so-called Canada
is basically the biggest critique I get
is silence it's just not something
people want to deal with right it's like
it's out of their bandwidth it's sort of
arcane it's all of those classic settler
tropes with respect to what that
relationship would be and if indeed
there is actually even a relationship on
the first nations or first peoples or
Inuit or matey side the discussion is
much different of course that's been a
non-stop discussion since since we had
first contact since we settlers landed
so that's a discussion that's been
ongoing but the relationship is
complicated because basically they see
for the most part that relationship is
with the crown and then maybe the
government that represents the crown so
we see that reflected even in the Truth
and Reconciliation the 24 car the 94
calls to action which after I reviewed
that basically had nothing to do nothing
for ordinary citizens to do it's all
about the institutions which have
already failed once now they're supposed
to somehow pick up the baton and move
forward and yet the whole nature of how
that relationship was created is is
incredibly flawed so the did obviously
the discussions about the doctrine of
discovery and manifest destiny are not
something that the government is ever
going to talk about and of course the
queen is just a figurehead so it's a
very interesting dynamic and so if you
could call silence a critique that's the
one I face and so I'm just trying to
break through that I know that that's
based on trust so there's there
it's an absolutely no trust between the
two parties for the most part so yeah
it's it's it's a work to try to
establish trust to try to establish in
that space that even as a citizen I
could sort of take responsibility for
that
and-and-and live up to duties and
obligations were you know they typically
first peoples are looking to the
government right to the crown as opposed
to a citizen so yeah I'm working through
all of those things and any suggestions
as to how to make that happen would be
greatly appreciated thank you Hey Thank
You Susan I will take my turn to share
it's just a bit of a hard question just
because I never really quite know the
umbrella fly project I've been trying to
create what is together tech what is the
technology cooperative and a solutions
cooperative for a very long time and the
biggest critique I get on that
overarching umbrella
besides that technology's the problem
not the solution is that things like
pick a thing pick a thing and go with it
and like pick a project and then people
will come on board and it doesn't work
with me because if it's like I want to
take them it the actions that come up as
they come up
it seems to be more conducive my life
but for solution raising in general I
don't think I've gotten much critique
it's not like the other ones because
it's an hour-long conversation that
people can can participate in they
understand that it's not about
necessarily creating the project at the
end it's about generating that and
having the conversation so I guess the
biggest critique is okay now how do we
create this in the world why does this
exist in the world when why doesn't it
because this the world isn't really my
critique yes let's get it in the world
let's figure out figure out that process
so I do know every critique I get helps
me to solidify what I'm here to do what
it is that it does and and move forward
with that so I appreciate critique I
guess I get a little frustrated I'm sure
most of us do and hearing the same
critique over and over again I
understand of course why that happens
those are the critiques we need to be
dealing with and at the same time like I
don't I want new ones to me so I can
address them like internally and
Solutions but that only happens with
let's say you have talked to 100 people
and maybe 1 1 in 100 or 1 in 10 comes up
with something new to critique or give
their opinion on it you wouldn't have
heard before and so that is my
experience now we can all an all though
it's kind of hard with five people so
I'm gonna unmute everyone and then you
guys can just take over your own mutant
abilities so that if you're not talking
and it's getting too loud you when
you're not talking about make sense but
otherwise yeah we can open up the
discussion this is the first idea cafe
that's specifically like I said 2
projects so I'll see how this goes
because now it's like well now what do
we talk about I guess the power of
critique or how you feel when people
critique it or anything that came up all
other people were we're talking well
having gone to art school Emily Carr
University and Vancouver critique is
nothing you should ever take personally
I learned that as a matter of fact in
art school the goal was to make you cry
or to try to make you cry so yeah just
don't take it personally so bring it on
I have no problems for the critique I'm
not gonna critique - but they're making
you cry I was preparing us for the real
world it's a real world is not art
school right it's like people will make
you cry you know I did want to say that
Susan on yours that that can be very
very challenging as kind of crickets I
do think I I think it is stronger in
your situation because it is a topic
that people would rather not not
approach at all and kind of forget it
exists like we have for hundreds of
years but also just a little
encouragement that I think we all kind
of feel that struggle with crickets and
our projects from time to time so even
though heat yours is a little bit more
challenging I don't know if it might
help to have a little encouragement that
that is something that we're all
struggling with
yes thank you I do feel encouraged it's
not like I don't get feedback but it
tends to be more I mean there is
listening people do listen and you know
somewhat like it like I'm active on
Twitter that was the first thing I did I
mean I have a UX design and UX research
background so obviously the first thing
I did was to go to the users and listen
for almost a good year before I even
started to do anything so I mean I'm
sort of gauging response that way so I
am getting feedback I'm not getting out
and out critique so that's basically you
know the other problem is that the
entire word Commons what is a Commons
what is a virtual Commons right I mean
this I had to drag up because settlers
this is our last experience of being you
know in common in relationship with the
land that was what was at 1500s before
the royalty came and took all the lands
and said basically these are ours right
and you're just gonna work on them so
yeah there's a couple of things that
throw people off right yeah so maybe I'm
a little confused on what you mean by
settlers which everyone is that maybe
part of the problem but seriously well I
mean well I mean so like I'm from
America so of the u.s. bad say America
so my I'm sure some of my ancestors were
some original settlers to the US other
ones came at no I guess both major
branches we're here yeah quite a long
time yeah so it requires that you dig
into your history it requires that you
actually try to think about you know
where you come from and who you are with
respect to your ancestors so again the
Crown's I wasn't sure if you cut that
off at a certain historical period well
yeah technically settlers would have to
have been around what seventeen
late 1700s I think into about mid 1800s
so for instance my my mother on my
mother's side they originally came from
Scotland settled or actually got
shipwrecked at around 1795 off the coast
of the Atlantic coast and went to that
little tiny island which they call
Prince Edward Island which actually
where the founding fathers gathered
right so we actually that was the
original Canada was very small the
original Canada and then it sort of
spread right so and the same thing can
happen in BC right so the two coasts
actually contain most of the original
settlers you know Montreal the East
Coast and the west coast and then in
between you had the treaties which
started to roll out so then the third
the third group are immigrants which
obviously are still included in a
conversation but it gets a little bit
you know you say settlers immigrants and
First Peoples it gets a little Inuit you
know so but the real important
connection the one which ties us all is
exploring that original relationship but
we are all treaty people even if you're
an immigrant even if you just got your
immigration status a year ago
you're still a treaty person because all
of Canada and United States is that was
under treaty is under treaty may
question although I don't know if we
want to focus on your project but that's
totally oh sure if you want but um was
my question I had it and then I loved it
like what oh yes do you need so the idea
that it's bringing together basically
settlers and first people the settlers
especially do they need to be people who
like is it more for people who want to
find out about that and or who are
invited to find out about this
connection or is it more for people who
honestly don't care and like is it the
interested settlers or the uninterested
settlers that this is more focusing on a
great question well the comments would
play a role in both of those sides but
if obviously the core group that would
be engaged
in discussion obviously you would have
to happen an interest in it otherwise
you wouldn't even show up for the
discussion but part of what I've worked
through with the UX research which you
know of course is very eye-opening with
respect to who's actually interested in
this project my assumption from the
start because I have a creative artistic
background would be that the artists
indigenous artists would be interested
they would think hey this is cool let's
work on this but not at all they have
their own projects then they're not in
the least bit interested in working with
settlers they've kind of finished with
settlers they're done right yeah for the
most part it's true they're just like
you go ahead with the response I would
get go ahead do your thing but the most
important thing is to help to decolonize
right the settler mind and you know get
them aligned with what it is that we
signed in the first place
yeah so that so what I found in was the
response came from settlers they are
interested they're out there they're
like what can we do so this whole idea
of collective karmic debt goes back to
the idea that it's a Buddhist idea but
it also you can be found in Christianity
that you actually have a debt a karmic
debt and in this case it's a collective
karmic debt it's the entire you know
Turtle Island Canada the United States
that has a debt we actually owe a debt
well that's really scary
because people immediately think that
you're gonna want to pull money out of
their pockets but which shows
immediately and you know nothing about
indigenous relationships because the
ninja steeples were never faith we're
never focused on money
that isn't it their relationships are
not the relationships are the most
valuable things so there's so many
important lessons that we can learn
through these discussions but again I
had to do the research in order to
discover even for myself who was
interested but yes settlers are very
interested typically they tend to be on
Twitter that's where I found them
they're not necessarily on Facebook
because Facebook is more about it's even
more of a bubble like you get in your
little bubble with your friends and
that's pretty much it we know that
bubble factor whereas Twitter is more
about politics and social issues so if
their ability to cross over and have
some little discussions does happen and
also to be able to listen to indigenous
thought leaders is available so there's
a learning listening process there and
then the again the task is how do we get
into a safe secure space because Twitter
is not safe it is not secure and of
course it's incredibly limited 140
characters I mean what kind of
discussion are you having right it's
actually a question I was because you
had mentioned the very high thing goes
before we went live that part of what
your vision is is to have a no trolling
on on this platform and I'm just
wondering how you see that being
enforced I feel like it's wrong but how
do you guarantee that how do you you
great question yeah so basically it's
through the technology obviously and it
has to be decentralized you have to be
agent centric so of course I've been
I've been working with the hollow chain
community or you know involved in that
ecosystem so it will be built built on
hollow chain so that first part of being
secure and decentralized I you know
that's what hollow chain affords so that
will be that'll be a given once that's
in play once that's the ability to build
that out happens then there I don't know
much I mean I do actually a lot about
hollow chain but probably not as much as
you do if you're involved with it do you
mean like their technology underlining
well we'll deal with the trolling as in
like they under the holo chain
decentralized umbrella they will figure
out how to ID people therefore you're
gonna be less likely to troll because
it's associated with you even if you're
somewhat commenting and like that they
figure out the unanimity part and so
therefore it spills over or what do you
mean it takes care of itself
I just don't well I mean the actual
space itself because it's decentralized
so the first thing is are we running
this through Zuckerberg living room
right you know no we are not we're not
running
we're not being so that high-level
trolling what we call surveillance
capitalism that's that's not happening
so that affords a little more levity in
discussions right then the second thing
I think what you're talking about is bad
actors right which is what I know
trolling as is Morgan I didn't think of
Facebook and Google as trolls I hope
that they have the surveillance part
going on it's just maybe a different
wording it yeah so secure and then
taking away the trolling so the trolling
part yeah would be the bad agents the
bad actors so that I think that would be
a process I mean indigenous peoples are
very good at asking the right questions
to determine who you are and what you're
all about they only have to ask you a
couple questions when they figure out
right for the most part your level of
engagement so the governance piece would
be you know coming from First Peoples
ideally and I've spoken to many
indigenous women who are interested in
the project they're just not sure you
know they can't really wrap their head
around what it is but they are kind of
standing by to see what actually you
know this space has to be created first
I think it's hard just conceptually for
them to go there in terms of to
visualize that that's not within their
culture they're very traditional and
they have closed systems right so that
that has to I think we have to have
something and invite them into that
space first but then the governance so
the rules the protocols of you know who
who is participating and how you
identify yourself will the determining
factor right but I think that'll be
it'll be easy to see that after a short
period of time right and then if you're
not really I I mean I see the process
more of them I've set up certain
challenges which you would have to go
through in order to to sort of establish
that you're authentically interested in
this as opposed to just we're open it up
for anybody when they just come on in
and create havoc yeah so again that's a
process we're not exactly at that point
yet
- onboarding yeah I just put my water
all over myself water is life there we
go I just felt like all over myself
yeah very much switching gears a little
bit I kind of want to pose a question to
the group about critique and how you use
like you have any examples of how you
use pratik to push your projects forward
or got some good ideas out of it so I
it's it's interesting we've been doing
quite a bit of kind of critique for
because of Jubilees idea cafes and stuff
like that again a lot of ideas and
having in the project raisings often
people are asking for feedback but we do
a good job I think of initially you know
asking whether they want feedback which
even if someone kind of gives the pat
answer it still prepares their mind for
some harshness so they they tend to be
more open-minded I don't think that
answers your question though goodbye can
you restate that yeah that's all just
curious about specificity that you face
for your project that you use it to
iterate your project and the critique
actually made it better yeah so early on
this this concept of people saying that
it's impossible or it's too big or
something like that because because they
kind of think I'm getting to an end-all
be-all score for these things
so just from the and also people were
thinking that it's a perfect what is it
they want anyway so I end up pre-empting
the confusion earlier in the in the
discussion or in the description of the
product so I say something like if we
can improve like people are thinking I'm
gonna get these two opposing the worst
like I'm gonna get you know two
completely opposing political people in
a room and have them agree on something
when really all I'm doing is increasing
the agreement so I changed my wording to
say you know bringing us closer to
agreement or stuff like that so that so
that people see it less in a black and
white idea so so I have I have changed
almost every time I talk to someone I do
end up heading my copy and now I have to
actually have several different versions
of it depending on the audience so
that's the way I've used the critique
and I'm sure I've included it in designs
because there are people like I might
have a symbol indicating the score and
they're like saying well is that full or
empty right so and that just comes back
to the UX where you find out a visually
way of you expressing it made certain
assumptions that other people don't have
or not everyone has and then that comes
into direct design changes so that's a
little bit of what I've done in the past
I think building a bit on on that I've
had the a very similar experience where
the critique sometimes it's used to
build and the product like if it's a
critique that I haven't thought of it
actually is a gap but I do find that in
most cases is actually a gap in the
content in the explanation of it that
now I have to go back and say how do I
explain this differently so that that
question is answered just you know by
the content itself and people don't have
to ask it and then continually getting
that kind of feedback and continually
improving the the messaging to explain
it but isn't that the same as UX
research I mean typically the critique
should come from the users right so
that's why you do UX testing yeah I'm in
in my case I'm kind of pre UX like I'm
sort of yeah exactly
but in the end yes it's still that sort
of the ability to sort of design and to
explain it is where in in my case at
least the critiques end up sort of
helping to patch that and update it is
the finding out why did the person have
that question
oh because I didn't you know talk about
this certain topic in that content how
do I add that how do I you know talk
about that in a way that's meaningful
and doesn't take four hours well yeah in
the startup space they call that the
disco
reprocess so you have to get out of the
office and you have to go to talk to the
people that will be using it or the
stakeholders or whoever is involved and
start to get some feedback just on your
concept alone right yeah that for me
when I've been getting critique on the
issues it helps me gain clarity as to
what wasn't explained the first time it
also comes with the other added layer if
like then I want to explain it all every
time because I've gotten this critique
before so you might not understand this
point as opposed to I find a
conversation is a great way to explain
it because then I can deal with that on
a one-on-one basis instead of trying to
answer all questions at once so it helps
me kind of generate almost like an FAQ
of common problems and then I can kind
of have one place to send them to but
I've yet to actually create that and
where it most helps me is my internal
reaction to what they say that how I
feel about what they say is my learning
for what I need how I need to move
forward there's times where people
critique it and it empowers me where I'm
like oh yeah that's not a problem like
because I the solutions are coming down
the road and then there's other times
where it does disempower me and then I
have to deal with why is that and why
why did their critique hit me in that
way why do I feel like it's a critique
on me as a person and I want to cry
about it as opposed to having it be open
so that's and I think also just
personally I deal with critique fairly
well I look for that like both
personally and for my project like I
want to know unless personally now now
I'm all about not don't critique me as a
person I want to know your critique on
my ideas and the solution because of
that I'm not changing me but I will
change this like this is ours this is
lying so I'm not gonna change my person
I'm gonna grow and evolve but like and
getting that is what I got through
critique because I would get there were
people who would comment to my YouTube
videos and be like how I look or how I'm
acting and I was like oh I'm actually
not down for I didn't mean to critique
that that's not what I meant I meant the
idea and so now when that happens I can
kind of just I'll deal with it and look
for the critique of the idea
nice I think I really when I got my
critiques it really made me focus on the
financial sustainability of the business
I'm trying to create and really spend a
lot of time with that I mean the it is
about critique someone with more money
or had C capital or an entrepreneurial
business background should be doing this
type of work or I should say is more fit
to do this type of work or qualified so
it's really helped me try to establish
where other urban agriculture ventures
have gone wrong which is not being
sustainably economically sustainable and
relying on grant money in volunteer work
and things like that so I feel like I
have a pretty good game plan of how I am
going to be able to sustainably generate
revenue through selling I work at a
hospital and my hospital has started out
some food pantries to give to the
community and they they purchased that
they have forty thousand one part of the
hospice forty thousand dollars budgeted
the other has fifty thousand a year
budgeted to buy things so has eaten up
with my place of employment to see if
they will purchase goods has kind of
been a good start for me
good we got our out of the office and
you went and talked to a stakeholders
good job what is your business model
Brad as far as I know a bunch of people
in that space but I don't know like
you're bringing food from into food
deserts but how are you doing that so
there are people who are food insecure
and there is a questionnaire when you
get there's like a hundred questions you
get asked when you come to a hospital
could be on safety whatever there's
three questions on food insecurity and
we're working with a committee at our
hospital called social determinants of
health to generate consults the social
worker people answer these questions
saying yes I don't have access to foods
I don't have the financial capabilities
that generates the console that social
worker then gives
materials to go to the pantry catch to
the hospital so 75% of what I intend to
grow I want to sell to the hospital so
they can provide the food to the people
that are answering these questionnaires
and qualifying for the food the other
25% there is a good entry down the road
for me now that I wanted to donate 25%
of my food to supply so 100% of
everything I am growing or tend to grow
is going to be given to people who are
food insecure but I don't have that app
answered your full question of business
model well I mean you're throwing food I
didn't know that before so you're
growing the food you're not just looking
to get it from people who are otherwise
growing the food and I'm bringing it
there's three people in that space that
that if you want to have a conversation
outside of this I'm happy to there's two
things three things they're being done
in Vancouver itself that I'm in contact
with them one way or another and then
also someone in the game B space who has
like an online farmers market oshika I
think is what it's called and they'd say
no to Utah and they have basically a
model to trade that in every city so to
create like that someone its
franchisable is what I'm trying to say
so it's open source of franchise well so
anyone in any city can take that on and
create a relationship between like the
purchaser and I'm wondering I don't know
if that would work within a space of
food insecure people it solves the food
desert
issue not the access to it because of
cost right so it like solves you have
access to it it's not necessarily that
it can be at a lower rate but you're
growing your food so you can make that
one available at the cost it is to you
so yeah so I'd be very interested
hearing that when when we're done kind
of link up with them just to kind of
further flesh out the business Molly and
growing mainly any grow berries some
greens nuts and seeds mainly but I'm a
dietitian by trade so I do provide
medical nutrition therapy that kind of
came up with like a master list of foods
that we use for medical nutrition
therapy and the ones that are obviously
lacking in places that don't have fresh
access to fresh foods so I'm kind of
using that pathway that that's what I am
intending to grow and okay feels more on
towards the game B idea because if
you're working in a game a space you
think what's the highest selling food oh
I should grow that versus I need this is
a food people need to be healthy or if
they wish to be healthy or want to
manage some of their current diseases
this is what they would need be provided
so kind of using that framework and the
social entrepreneurship framework and
then Carol Sanford's when Tibbles put a
couple bottom line which is kind of just
all the stakeholders that are attached
your business whether it be the
community the co-creators the investors
the planet etc and a quick question for
Susan when you're talking about the
settlers I had a really thing like am I
like settler my family came in 1920 is
the United States and then you've kind
of answered that but a follow-up
question to that is what percent of the
population and kinder elsewhere you know
our actual settlers versus immigrants or
does that even matter to us well that's
a great question because you know I talk
about business models and you know
viability you know how many people
settlers would be really engaged in this
conversation or you know but I took my
cue from an indigent and indigenous
scholar and lawyer
Pam Paul Matar who is out of Ryerson
University Jubilee you may have heard of
her
okay so anyhow she's very active and
she's an activist as well as a professor
and educator so she's written a number
of books on indigenous sovereignty and
indigenous rights and so on but in one
of the books she wrote she actually says
in her opinion there's at least 100,000
now they call she calls them allies in
Canada so I'm assuming the majority of
those would have to be conscious as to
where they came from right but that
doesn't necessarily mean that there's
not immigrants you know who who
recognize that this land was indigenous
to you know different nations and before
the settlers arrived right so you know
again it has to do with really knowing
where you come from which when you look
at indigenous relationships and how they
introduce themselves the first thing
they'll do is refer to their
grandfathers and their grandmothers and
their ancestors I mean that's part of
their their ways right so that's not
part of our ways so this is where the
conversation gets really interesting
right we would like to forget where we
came from you know happy is the country
that forgets its history us basically
Canada United States because in that act
of forgetting we erase indigenous
peoples thank God
we erase our own history too we don't
know where we come from I mean you asked
the average Canadian where they come
from and they'll say they're Canadian
and you're like doesn't mean anything
right you know you know did you know
that you're actually a British subject
until 1982 something which I discovered
in the last week for God's sakes
right I thought I was a Canadian from
that idea I was born I'm actually was a
British citizen until 1982 so what the
hell does that mean I'm watching now of
this series of the crown you know my
mother would be a staunch supporter of
the Queen every time the Queen's rolled
through town which was Edmonton tar
sands area you know we she would try to
drag us out to see the Queen but I was
like I'm not going to see the Queen what
is that nothing to do with me right
because again my mother never taught me
any of that right even though she had
this long seven generation family tree
which I now possess which someone took
you know hours and weeks and months to
compile there's still no reference to
indigenous cultures in there we're just
like this long chain of Scottish people
who came to the you know open land and
you know started our thing right so yeah
it's a really it's a really wicked
problem it's really thorny but and it
involves history but you know that's
well that's we're engaged in right now
is a historical moment where we're all
experiencing so this whole Kovan thing
is another conversation that we now
share you know first peoples as settlers
and immigrants were all in this we're
all trying to make sense of this so this
is like this is like a huge so yeah
these are defining moments with respect
to trying to figure out who we are and
why we're here and what we're doing I
know for me two of the things and what I
would love to have access to as a is the
difference between the traditions that
were on Turtle Island first like what is
the difference in culture and language
and all of these things because I we are
part Cherokee and I don't know enough
about that
and so I've grown up in Canada in
Alberta with those tribes and then here
with like with these nations and for the
last 20 years and so part of what I'm
drawn to is the west coast ones I have a
childhood this is boring why are we
learning this attach which of the
Alberta ones because they don't have you
to put you're introduced to and what I
want is my roots from from that and I
don't know what's what and then from my
European side any history we learn is
like colonial history but it's the kings
and queens it's not like what are my
actual traditions and so to give anyone
access to their roots you kind of need
to give everyone access to their roots
of like what did it look like to be in
Scotland in Wales in Ireland 200 years
ago not for the candy Queen but for you
know potato farmers that we probably
were how can I track my genetics and to
know kind of actually what what what I
am but even more so because I've had I'm
always based in tech of like a history
the idea of a history a project that we
we put in together that you can like
zoom in and out of history and part of
my I didn't go and talk to people in on
the grounds but like I knew from my
experience that a lot of First Nations
don't want their information out there
because their information and so like
that I know yeah so where that where
that
comes together is the reason that the
Commons is called the Touro flow
cultural Commons is that the grandfather
treaty of all treaties was a two row
wampum treaty I don't know if you're
familiar with that actually with the
Mohawk Ojibwe who - who - only peoples
and the Dutch settlers around 1630 one
New York area you know that New York New
Jersey sort of area so that was the
grandfather of all treaties which was
created with the Dutch and the the
premise of that it is when I took a look
at that I was like I'm an information
architect and there we have a framework
a protocol that was set up by the Chiefs
so basically the metaphor is that we're
both in our boats going down the river
so first peoples are in their canoe
we're in our you know sailing ships
we're both travelling down the river
together the same river the the goal is
to travel together but not to interfere
with one another but we should know each
other's ways and customs and laws at a
higher level we're not talking about
sacred ceremonies and knowledge that's
sacred that's not what we're looking for
we're talking about a general
understanding of what indigenous law
means right what their ways and their
customs represent to them right and
obviously again you have this
asymmetrical balance because they know a
ton more about us than we know any we
don't nothing literally zilch about most
indigenous cultures and that is again
this the the other narrative which is
apartheid which if you go through
historical records the founding fathers
were aware of the fact that if
indigenous peoples and settlers got
together there could be a whole
different dynamic the same thing in
America you know you can include that in
African Americans and then later into
Canada the same dealio right if you get
those two groups together you know not
the ruling class but the working class
and then the indigenous peoples and the
African slaves you're gonna have a lot
of trouble so we have actually been kept
apart this is a
system that has been designed an
information system that's been in design
from the start with a very explicit goal
and that is to keep us separated keep us
apart and hence we have the word
apartheid so yeah not knowing anything
about your culture where you come from
and who you're connected to that's all
part of the system right so we need to
recognize that and try to break through
that that's why it's very important that
settlers getting mate engaged it's just
a part of overarching critique on
anything we do together is how do you
decide what gets included and what
doesn't get included for instance if
there is the og boy with nation and they
get together and say this is what we're
willing to share that is clear that's
what you share but if one person from
that nation is like I'm good hears
everything everything that my grandma
and grandpa taught me and I want to
share it is it theirs to share or do you
you know what I mean like how what group
level do you have to do that on because
in what I'm creating it's like well the
co-operators and the shares Trump the
other ones right because it's like one
person shares it's shared at the same
time that doesn't honor especially in
this in this realm right but like it
isn't necessarily ours to share it was
because it's yours to share well then
again you get into individual versus
collective ways of being so most
indigenous peoples that I know I you
know they know what to share and what
not to share again they just like they
know where they come from and who their
ancestors are this is their way of life
right so it's not likely that they're
going to share anything that they know
that they shouldn't share right you know
so again when I did my research with UX
settlers or the UX research with the
settlers I asked them how do they find
their information about first peoples
like where is it coming from and what do
they find interesting and could they
please blog about it and put their
personal spin on it and then fit it into
one of those frameworks so it's either
going to go under indigenous laws
indigenous ways that are indigenous
customs right so that they can try to
you know put it under a big cat
so typically again the stuff you find
online you know there's a lot of
information about indigenous cultures
but it's not culturally specific like
you're not gonna find out how they do
the ceremonies like all this stuff is
out in the public sphere right there's a
ton of information out there but nobody
archives that nobody categorizes no
there's no central place where you can
get this information so if you just wake
up one day and say hey I have a duty
responsibility to treaty how do I act on
that what do I know right where are you
gonna go to find that information you're
gonna spend a lot of time like I spent
10 years thinking about this right you
do even to arrive at the space last week
where I discover I was a British citizen
until 1982 right like that you know
there's just no one central space where
you can sort of quickly get up to speed
and try to understand what first peoples
already know all pretty much about our
culture like they know a ton about us
right so mm-hmm
but bitly if I wanted to ask you so
you're doing something impossible
bringing together opposing sounds sort
of like what I'm doing like two
different parties that it's about bring
them together so how are you overcoming
those like getting those users together
how like well I haven't gotten actually
getting people together and my project
is around very specific details like if
people were arguing on the topic of what
you know what year should we stop the
categorization of settler since there
are specific issues yeah then then yeah
my system allows them to put in kind of
like pros and cons and counter-arguments
and stuff and then it uses some math to
kind of say well based on the evidence
or the information that's been provided
here's the score the system has so far
as a guide to kind of figure out what's
in there and then it that it helps
people to explore their unspoken
objections or or even their emotional
things in there and then helps as a
group that group kind of get it together
so it's it's similar to yours in that
you know our dealing with a lot of
emotions and dealing with contentious
issues and people that might be arguing
and misunderstanding a lot the
difference is that my system can only
handle very I started from the bottom up
as far as complexity it can only handle
really simple things right now and then
as I grow it'll be able to handle
hopefully broader and broader topics
it's called reason score at reason score
calm so if you ever want to check that
out and yeah definitely if you if you
have any contentious issues that you
think could work I'm looking for smaller
problems not like climate change or
stuff like that I do know a group that's
working on stuff like that but smaller
like specific things like Adria and I
were talking about a pit bull ban and
Denver as kind of a topic to explore
using this tool so it's actually a tool
that you would open source code
algorithm like how do it does it and
then you could plug it in and the end of
the day is that what it's gonna be or is
it a standalone sort of app like you're
building it's open-source software and
it's kind of meant to be I think it'll
end up being a plug-in to other things
like loomio or some you know any other
tool so it might be something that your
community might or that you know the the
tech that you're building it might be a
feature a good little feature if if it
if it's useful so it's kind of like a
rating mmm-hmm is that with you as
opposed to people voting on whether
something's like they agree or disagree
with the point it it says if you
disagree with it tell us why and then
and you don't have duplication of
reasons a reason should only be in there
once you might change the wording of the
reason to be more specific or more clear
so it kind of reduces duplication makes
a little bit harder to troll to jubblies
concept because it's not as simple as
writing a comment and the person doesn't
win that either gets the most popularity
or the most
and actually people don't win because
it's a specific topic and you don't even
know who and usually you don't even know
who put in that claim or that piece of
evidence because it's not in the end
it's not important when you're trying to
make a group decision true-true
sounds fascinating yeah and yeah I'll be
having some experiments soon out and any
feedback like we say feedback you could
try and make me cry a few well I'm uh
protective I'm up for testing one of the
most important things yeah yeah got it
I'm just to that point it's just that
like everywhere every time I bring it up
like just showing it to a drill this
morning I found like four or five things
it's like oh it's still not quite even I
mean it's enough to get feedback but
it's not enough that I want to hand out
to a lot of people because there's some
obvious flaws that I just need to fix
over the next week or two
oh yeah I appreciate any help and
Jubilee you mentioned is something about
an hour long conversation what is that
what does that mean like how do you is
solution raising is a generative
hour-long conversation it's broken into
three parts so for 15 minutes we talk
about what is currently being done in
that sector and then we spend 15 minutes
talking about our individual ideal
versions of the future and then we spend
30 minutes talking about what is
something we could create right now if
we had 10,000 people and $100,000 and so
we've done seven of them today on things
like transportation and education the
most recent run on Wednesday was on
mental health and it was on it was live
on the one I do I go live every morning
at 8:30 and so I'm gonna do that
continually for Wednesdays have people
come in and participate in the live and
then I'll figure out it's right now it's
a Facebook group and it's YouTube and
all of the other solution reasons that
were pre-recorded or on this channel
together Tech whereas the other ones
because if when I go live I go live on
Jubilee saves the world Channel so I
figure you know that dynamic um where it
gets posted on Facebook and stuff is
what I'm kind of currently figuring out
cuz I have new ideas and I want to run
with them and like where to put them and
how they they incorporate with together
tech and stuff is is part of what so
your facility
hating conversations then around like
people will propose let's do it around
this let's do it around that and you're
facilitating you is that yeah yeah we're
picking different topics and doing that
there's that like I said there's the
Facebook group where the idea was anyone
could start one so you even though we've
had one on education anyone could do one
on education and have it different
people so but that is as most of the
ideas it doesn't it didn't generate in
that way it is yes I'm the one who needs
to facilitate all of them it appears so
I have been facilitating them and
eventually hopefully they'll move on to
zoom or there will be more people are
dissipating in it than Gerry we have to
do water on treaty treaty making are you
making fun of me making sense of
treating I don't just want to say treaty
making cuz those are done but making
sense of treaty making treaties right
are you making that would be great yeah
we're like it might be it's usually a
more broad topic like indigenous relate
like First Peoples settler relations
right what does that currently look like
we love that to look like and then what
could we do now with ten thousand
hundred thousand I think it'd be harder
to do that with the treaty making just
because people need your service first
to kind understand what that is in order
to be able true yeah the others have to
have that that conversation would be
amazing I mean you can call a
reconciliation whatever you want to call
it right but the whole idea of
reconciling you know we're in a period
of reconciliation right so that is
basically what we're supposed to be
doing right but when we say we of course
again it's hand it all off to the
institutions and citizens like okay
they'll handle it but no handle it well
to do that yeah with most things so
we're coming down to our last five and a
half minutes
oh nice answer can I ask about your wiki
as it aired Rio Adria Adria can I ask
about your wiki because my whole settler
UX research ended up with oh we need a
wiki yeah tell me about yours
so the name is like kind of descriptive
it sort of makes me two different things
it's kind of meant to be a wiki on
elections and
and politicians and parties and sort of
their history and that type of thing but
then it's also meant to be a tool where
people can sort of vote or left on
information
so really it's focused on three main
areas it's focused on like politics and
elections it's focused on being able to
sort of have evidence-based
conversations to figure out you know
who's telling the truth and where things
actually lie through the controversial
issues so like as Bentley sort of said
his de starting from the the bottom and
working up Lyons got a starting from the
top and working down and I'm a shooting
to shoot shooting high and the first two
topics that I want to cover are vaccines
and climate change well and then the
third part is sort of the tools needed
to have that conversation is kind of a
news aggregate tool almost where as
information is processed and has experts
weigh in on the various parts we'll
start to get sort of you know it
snapshot of how all the different
sources of information are talking about
the same topic have the community review
all that and start to see you know who's
telling the truth who has good evidence
who you know is using qualified experts
that kind of thing and part of it is
being able to take something sort of
complex like the legislation like
treaties and then having people like
actually uploading the content and then
having people like heading experts
dissect it and saying you know well this
part means this and this part means that
a bunch of experts do that and then you
can look at what are the experts in okay
you say you're an expert in law but
you're an expert in corporate law how
does that you know why are you talking
about now
treaties and it might not be the same as
somebody who specializes in tree and
history and this and that and being able
to sort of take all that into account
wonderful I like that so that's the
truth part of the truth and
reconciliation we need you know a lot of
first people say first we need to get
the truth out we haven't even got the
truth out never find a reconciliation
yeah is very valuable to us
yeah if you're interested I would love
to do like a a live stream and pick your
brain and sort of show you some of this
stuff
see what kind of questions you yeah
because yeah yeah we're kicking off all
the right boxes here
sure sure thank you thank you but I feel
like this is just like generated in my
head does our cousin dinner I know our
cousin went to school for law did they
not take she not take indigenous law
ethically right Wow
I think she's in Whitehorse yeah cool so
we could get her on possibly yeah yeah I
think she's I can invite on Facebook I
think she's you know at home like the
rest of us sure mohawk woman who is a
treaty scholar so the two of them could
have a great conversation a few of us
could you know listen and learn and
maybe we could get some other people I
mean even to talking about treaty would
be awesome and she's like she just
completed her law degree two years ago
maybe Wow I think so she's she's I'm 40
and she's like almost 10 years older
than me so she got her lunch she did an
engineering degree I remember what else
she did something else and now she's
going and then she went to become a lot
and so Jubilee you're from Alberta
rich yeah yeah what part of Alberta we
were born in Edmonton and raised in I
say we cuz a drill and iron siblings and
then you moved to the west coast yeah
individually collectively I just wanted
to mention this was gonna um to Ernesto
who had made two amazing comments that
the idea Cafe is the only one we do
where I don't interact with it messages
because it's about the conversation but
both of the comments were specifically I
believe for Suzanne's project so I will
copy and paste them and send them to her
because they were good comments about
stuff they see on in Central America
which is his focus as well as using the
arts for like that we need more more
depiction of people in the arts that is
is a way to of course move
reconciliation forward looking it down
to our last moment
that's why I assume that's why I assume
that indigenous people would be
interested because it was I think it was
Louis Riel who said it would be the
artist who will lead the revolution
right
but hey yeah and there I wanted me sir
the time leg is taking out the torch
other a good old technology that
although you don't need to answer it
your closing statements by any stretch
if anyone has a we do this every other
week on Fridays and in between we have
our together tech or meeting which is
more of the meta project helping the
project's facilitate each other and how
can we move that meta project forward
which we do next week during this time
we do interact with the comments but if
anyone has an idea for two weeks from
now for an idea cafe on a question that
can be generated for our projects I am
more than open to suggestions from
everywhere and anyone as to what that is
and then on Saturday mornings we do our
roundtable it's at 9:00 a.m. Pacific
Standard Time so that's about three
hours four hours ago
so three hours of four minutes started
and everyone can bring their project
give a brief description of what it is
what you've been up to possibly what
you're taking on for the next week or
you know however long until you come
again and anything you need help with
dream that we could probably potentially
help with and crowdsource for so that is
what together tech is doing and we have
our own Facebook group which is the
project which is game B projects
Facebook group where everyone who has a
game beat a project is welcome to come
and join and have a come I met a
conversation on how we can bring our
projects into the world because the
world needs them now more than ever and
so if anyone is if anyone has any
closing statements you can say them now
otherwise he is a quiet you know a
closing statement but building a bit on
what you just talked about
I think Bentley and I talked about
possibly next week's session reviewing
the prototype for sort of the game those
are not the game be yeah I guess the
game be project list like that
be together tech like actually taking a
look at that so it's possible that the
session following that might be just the
idea cafe on something that comes out of
that discussion on what does this need
to do what shouldn't it do what are the
next steps
what have we overlooked you know what's
actually
needed for the MVP because this is
probably still quite a few steps prior
to that and you're talking about
specifically the thing that you made
right consents me is our name for it
just the together tech prototype I guess
okay cuz Brad that is I said when I said
Adriel is working on one that is what I
was talking about so if you want to join
us next Friday Trey this time here and
we will be talking about more of that
that platform I me can always send it in
advance in fact I think we should post
it in the Facebook group to sit to get
feedback and say hey we're talking about
this right because although I know it's
in its infancy that's the time that's
the time to do that fair enough
or it grows up into an unruly toddler
and you gotta like deal with all of your
previous message alright so does anyone
else have any closing statements they'd
like them alright everyone can just stay
put and we will say goodbye to Facebook
and YouTube see you tomorrow morning